Guide to the Milton Charles Winternitz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Milton Charles Winternitz papers
1898-1959
MS 859
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
(10 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, lectures, printed matter, and memorabilia. The correspondence is made up largely of family correspondence, with a smaller amount of professional letters. Among his professional papers are lectures on pathology, offprints of his articles (1908-1946) and scrapbooks (1898-1954). Included also are letters of condolence to his family and biographical sketches on his death in 1959.
Winternitz, M. C. (Milton C.), 1885-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Library, 1978 and 1979.
Arrangement
Arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Milton C. Winternitz: teacher of pathology at Johns Hopkins Medical School, 1907-1917; pathologist at Johns Hopkins Hospital, 1910-1917; pathologist, City Hospital, Baltimore, 1910-1917; professor of pathology and bacteriology, Yale University, 1917-1950; professor emeritus, 1950-1959; dean of Yale Medical School, 1920-1935; administrator of various institutes and organizations; author of several books on medical topics.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, lectures, printed matter, and memorabilia. The correspondence is made up largely of family correspondence, with a smaller amount of professional letters. Among his professional papers are lectures on pathology, offprints of his articles (1908-1946) and scrapbooks (1898-1954). Included also are letters of condolence to his family and biographical sketches on his death in 1959.
Medicine -- Study and teaching; Educators; Pathologists; Physicians; Stock, C. C. (Charles Chester), 1910-; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957; Winternitz, M. C. (Milton C.), 1885-1959; Winternitz, William Welch; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Inventory, 1898-1959; 9.5 linear feet (9 paige boxes, 1 archive box)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1)
  - Notes on a European trip, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Book of letters of condolence, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Personal scrapbooks, 7 binders, 1898-1954 (Box 2)
  - Books (Box 3)
  - Books by Milton C. Winternitz and books from his library (Box 4)
  - Honors (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with Dr. William H. Welch (Box 5)
  - Lectures on pathology (Box 5)
  - Letters received upon MCW's resignation, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Letters of condolence addressed to Dr. William Winternitz on the death of MCW, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1945 (Box 5)
    - Thomas Watson Winternitz (Box 6)
    - Elizabeth Winternitz (Box 6)
    - Felix Winternitz (Box 6)
    - Mary Watson Winternitz (Box 6)
    - Jane Kimball Winternitz (Box 6)
    - Mary and William Winternitz (Box 6)
    - William Welch Winternitz (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - William Winternitz (Box 7)
    - Elizabeth Winternitz (Box 7)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Watson (Box 7)
    - Others (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Elizabeth Winternitz (Box 8)
    - C.-E. A. Winslow, 1935-1946 (Box 8)
    - Dr. C. Chester Stock (Box 8)
    - Warner Institute for Therapeutic Research (Box 8)
    - Mrs. Albert Tipple (Box 8)
    - Dr. H. A. Weiner (Box 8)
    - U.S. Rubber Co., talks (Box 8)
    - "Letters to the children,", 1930-1936 (Box 8)
    - Col. John R. Wood, 1942-1950 (Box 8)
    - Others (Box 8)
  - Correspondence:
    - "Letters to the children" (Box 9)
    - Mrs. M. C. Winternitz (Box 9)
- 1979 April Addition, Accession 1979-M-005; 83; (1 box)
  General note
  (xerox copy made for preservation purposes)
  Scope and Contents
  The number of items are contained in parentheses before the date.
  - Reprint, "Milton Charles Winternitz, February 19, 1885 - October 3, 1959," (2) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reprint, "Dean Winternitz and the Yale School of Medicine," (1), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reprint, "An unrecognized pathway for bacterial invasion of the respiratory tract," (1), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reprint, "Effect of intrabronchial insufflation of acid," (1), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reprint, "Epithelial proliferation following the intrabronchial insufflation of acid," (1), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reprint, "Production of pulmonary infarcts by the insufflation of acid," (1), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reprint, "Lesions of the respiratory tract initiated by the inhalation of irritating gases," (2), 1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reprint, "The pathology of influenza," (1), 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Galley proof and typescript of "Importance of laboratory and post-mortem findings," (2), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reprint, "Views as to causes of coronary sclerosis," (2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incomplete reprint, biographical sketch of Winternitz, (3), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reprint, "Medical School now an "Honors" college," (2), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reprint, "Stomatologic research at Yale University," (1), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Reprint, "Medical and dental education," (1), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reprint, "A new educational pattern," (1), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Xerographic copy of reprint, "Physician, meet the tooth," (1), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reprint, "A physician looks at mental hygiene," (1), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pamphlet, "Recreational facilities at the Human Welfare Group," (2), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reprint, "Yale University physical plan of the Human Welfare Group," (3), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Book review, (1), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Reprint, "Studies in the pathology of vascular disease," (1), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Reprint, "A Study in of the behavior of di-(hydroxymethyl)-peroxide in vivo and in vitro and its effect on the catalase activity of the blood," (1), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Reprint, "Experimental infectious angiitis," (1), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reprint, "Myocardial lesions resulting from dietary deficiency," (1), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Reprint, "Lesions of the larger vessels following renal artery constriction," (1), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Reprint, "The Effect of hypophysectomy on compensatory renal hypertrophy in dogs," (1), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Reprint, "Studies on the relation of the kidney to cardiovascular disease," (2), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Reprint, "The brain in experimental vascular disease," (1), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reprint, "The fall in blood pressure associated with intravenous injection of tissue extracts," (1), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Reprint, "Experimental studies in vascular disease," (1), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Reprint, "Meat extractives and the non-protein nitrogen of the blood," (1), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Reprint, "Necrosis of the renal pelvis associated with obstruction of the ureters," (1), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Reprint, "Some aspects of the relation of the kidneys to cardiovascular disease," (1), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Reprint, "The effect of low potassium diet and of desozycortcosterone acetate upon renal size," (1), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Reprint, "Studies on therapy in traumatic shock," (1), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Reprint, "Renal disease consequent upon the intravenous injection of low viscosity methyl cellulose," (1), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Reprint, "Studies on mechanisms involved in shock and its therapy," (1), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Reprint, "The relation of adrenalin and of the carotid sinus to the hyperglycemia of shock," (1), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Reprint, "Factors concerned with the induction of tourniquet shock," (1), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Reprint, "The differentiation of potassium from other agents associated with the toxic effects of tourniquet shock," (1), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Yale Alumni Weekly, (1), 1937 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Reprint, "Tuberculosis of the stomach; tuberculosis cavities of the liver; with report of a case," (1), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Reprint, "A case of sigmoid kidney," (1), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Reprint, "Tuberculosis of the parathyroid gland and its relation to the occurence of tetany in tuberculous meningitis," (1), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Reprint, "The catalytic activity of the blood in the toxemias of pregnancy," (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Reprint, "Primary melanotic sarcoma of the ovary," (1), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Reprint, "A unique coincidence of multiple subcutaneous haemangioendothelioma, multiple lymphangioendothelioma of the intestinal tract and multiple polypi of the stomach undergoing malignant changes; associated with generalized vascular sclerosis and cirrohosis of the liver," (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Reprint, "On the relation of the catalytic activity of the blood to the number of red blood cells in health, and to the number of white blood cells and the body temperature in peritonitis," (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Reprint, "Observations upon the action of salts on the catalase of the blood in rabbits," (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Reprint, "On the occurrence of lipase in human tissues and its variation in disease," (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Reprint, "The determination of the catalytic activity of the blood as a clinical diagnostic method," (1), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Reprint, "The clinical value of the determination of the catalytic activity of the blood," (1), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Reprint, "The effect of occlusion of the various hepatic vessels upon the liver," (1), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Reprint, "Tuberculosis of the spleen," (1), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Reprint, "Primary carcinoma of the liver," (2), 1912, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Reprint, "The pathology of syphilitic aortitis with a contribution to the formation of aneurysm," (1), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Reprint, "Studies upon experimental pneumonia in rabbits, Parts I-IX," (7), 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Reprint, "The role of the autopsy in the medicine of today," (1), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Reprint, "Chronic lesions of the respiratory tract," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Reprint, "Edema of the lungs as a cause of death," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Reprint, "Anatomical changes in the respiratory tract initiated by irritating gases," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Reprint, "Intrapulmonary irrigation," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Reprint, "Experimental nephropathy in the dog," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Reprint, "Mesarteritas of the pulmonary artery," (1), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 65)